Finding Aid for Ali A. Mazrui papers, 1959-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Writings by Mazrui
  - "Economic Divergence, Cultural Convergence and the Politics of the East African Community," conference paper January 1976 (Box 2)
  - "Education and Cultural Diversity in Black Africa: A Regional Case Study," Mazrui and Teshome Wagaw undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Education and Culture Conflict in Eastern Africa: A Regional Case Study," Mazrui and Teshome G. Wagaw, conference paper September 1980, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Education and Elite Formation in East Africa," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Educational Dependency and the New International Cultural Order: The African University as a Case Study," Mazrui and B.E. Kipkorir and Niara Sudarkasa, conference paper October 1978, typescript (Box 2)
  - "The Educational Implications of National Goals and Political Values in Africa," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Educational Techniques and Problems of Identity in Plural Societies," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Electoral Horizons in Africa," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "The Emergence of Documentary Radicalism in East Africa," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Escape from Underdevelopment: African Intellectuals in Search of Refuge," conference paper January 1979, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Ethnic Tensions and Political Stratification in Uganda," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Ethnicity and National Integration in Africa's Experience: A Re-Assessment," conference paper August 1989, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Ethnicity and the Political Geography of Violence in Black Africa," conference paper March 1979, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Ethnicity, Power and Population in Eastern Africa," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Eulogy to Steve Biko," September 1977, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Eurafrica, Eurabia and Afro-Arab Relations: The Tensions of Tripolarity," conference paper 1980, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Eurafrica: A Clash of Cultures in Seven Dimensions," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "European Exploration and Africa's Self-Discovery," offprint from Journal of Modern African Studies, vol. 4, 1969, undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Exit Visa from the World System,", typescript and offprint (Box 3)
    (from Third World Quarterly January 1981)
  - "The Fall of Idi Amin and the Defeat of Muhammad Ali," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Foreword to Allen, James de Vere, translation of Al-Inkishafi," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Foreword to Gwyn Amin: Death-Light of Africa," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Foreword," to Osolo-Nasubo A Socio-Economic Study of the Kenya Highlands from 1900-1970 (Washington, D.C.: University Press of America), 1977, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Francophone Nations and English-Speaking States: Imperial Ethnicity and African Political Formations," symposium paper June 1981, typescript (Box 3)
  - "The Frankenstein State and the Tensions of Uneven Sovereignty: Towards a More Civilized Power-Sharing," conference paper October 1988, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Freedom in Uganda and I," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Chapter 12: From Dulles and Nasser to Kissenger and Sadat: The Triumph of Pragmatists," Mazrui and Hasu H. Patel, book chapter undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "From Pax Britannica to Pax Americana,", typescript (Box 3)
    (for Callander Lectures at University of Aberdeen, Scotland, March 1984)
  - "From Rural to Urban Terrorism in Africa," WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "From Social Darwinism to Current Theories of Modernization: A Tradition of Analysis," conference paper December 1967, typescript (Box 3)
  - "The Computer Culture and Nuclear Power: Political Implications for Africa," conference paper November 1979, typescript (Box 3)
  - "From the Semites to the Anglo-Saxons: Culture and Civilization in Changing Communication," conference paper April 1985, typescript and reprint (Box 3)
    (from Alternatives, 1986)
  - "From Social Darwinism to Current Theories of Modernization: A Tradition of Analysis," conference paper December 1967, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Fuel and Federalism in Relations Between Nigeria and the United States," WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "The Functions of Anti-Americanism in African Political Development," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Gandhi, Marx and the Warrior Tradition in African Resistance: Towards Androgynous Liberation," conference paper August 1976, typescript (Box 3)
  - "The Gender Gap in African Sports," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Gender, Skill and Power: Africa in Search of Transformation," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Geography Versus Commonwealth Loyalties: A Continuing Dialectic," conference paper May 1969, typescript (Box 3)
  - "George Orwell on Privacy," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Global Structures for World Order in the 1990s" undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Growing Up in A Shrinking World: A Private Vantage Point," book chapter 1989 and earlier draft, undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Harambee: People's Participation in Development," lecture July 1974, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Health and H2O: Africa's Crisis of Clean Water," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Heroic Yes, Successful No," Africa Events May-June 1986 (Box 3)
  - "Hostages in Africa's Experience," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Human Obligation and Global Accountability,", typescript (Box 3)
    ("Written in honor of Saul H. Mendlovitz," November 1988)
  - "Human Rights and Social Justice Through World Culture," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Human Rights and the Moving Frontier of World Culture," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Human Rights and the New International Moral Order," conference paper July 1980, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Human Rights and the Three Worlds of Power," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Hussein's Fall: Was It Martyrdom or an Assassination?" undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "'I Am Black But Oh My Soul Is White,'" undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Ideas and Idolatry in Africa," galley from Times History of Our Times, undated (Box 3)
  - "Ideological and Intellectual Encounters of the Third World: An Overview," conference paper August 1982, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Ideology and Political Thought in the Third World," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Ideology and Race-Mixture in Portuguese-Speaking Africa," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "The Ideology of Pragmatism in Africa," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Idi Amin Versus Jimmy Carter: A Moral Cleavage Between North and South," in Trialogue, Fall 1978 (Box 3)
  - "The Impact of Transnational Corporations on Educational Processes and Culture Change: An African Perspective," conference paper, November 1976, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Imperial Winds of Change: From Winston Churchill to Harold Macmillan," 1979 BBC Reith lecture, typescript (Box 3)
  - "In Search of a New Interdependence," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "In Search of Authenticity," Mazrui and Mohamed Bakari undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "In Search of East African Unity," WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "In Search of Pax Africana," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Independent East Africa," book chapter undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Intellectuals in African Politics: Present Decline and Future Recovery," conference paper January 1979, typescript (Box 3)
  - "International Stratification and Third World Solidarity," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "The Intifadah in Palestine and the Student Movement in China,", typescript (Box 3)
    ("mainly based on a lecture given by Professor Mazrui on behalf of the Palestine Aid Society, Ann Arbor Chapter, on June 9, 1989")
  - "The Invisible Passenger," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Is Africa Decaying?" undated, typescript (Box 3)
    ("based on a chapter written for Uganda Now" (pub. 1988))
  - "Is Africa's Westernization Reversible?" undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Is Energy Conservation in the West Detrimental to Third World Interests?" undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Is Israel A More Open Society Than the United States?", typescript (Box 3)
    ("written for The Michigan Daily, Ann Arbor, Michigan, September 1988")
  - "Is Israel a Nuclear Power?", typescript (Box 3)
    ("prepared for the United Nations Group of Experts on Israel's Nuclear Armament, 1980-1981")
  - "Is Modernization Reversible? An African Perspective," conference paper July 1985, typescript (Box 3)
  - 'Is The Satanic Verses A Racist Novel?", typescript (Box 3)
    ("extract from a lecture... delivered at Cornell University in March 1989")
  - "Islam and Competitive Religion in Africa," in The Reporter, January 12, 1990 (Box 3)
  - "Islam and Nuclear Peril,", typescript (Box 3)
    (lecture delivered at Cornell, 1988)
  - "Islam and the English Language in East and West Africa," conference paper, December 1968, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Islam and the New International Religious Order: Some African Perspectives," conference paper May 1979, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Islam in Africa and the New International Religious Order," undated, typescript, two drafts (Box 3)
  - "Islam in African Society,", typescript (Box 3)
    (four lectures delivered at Oxford Centre for Islamic Studies, 1987)
  - "Islam in East Africa," book galleys undated (Box 3)
  - "Islam, Marxism and Militancy in Africa," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Islam, Political Leadership and Economic Radicalism in Africa," 1968, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Islam: The Ethical and the Legal," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Islamic Law and Comparative Economics," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Israel Between 1967 and 1968" undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Jomo Kenyatta," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Judeo-Christian Universalism and the Ethnocentrism of Western Social Science," conference paper August-September 1988, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Julius K. Nyerere and Gamal Abdul Nasser," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "Kaunda's Attitude to Violence," undated newspaper clipping from identified newspaper (Box 3)
  - "The Kennedy-Johnson Era of Afro-American Relations," undated, typescript (Box 3)
  - "The King, the King's English, and I: A Personal Narrative," undated, typescript, with separate preface (Box 4)
  - "Kiswahili International: Is It the Only International Language that Africa Has Produced?" lecture July 1974, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Kwame Nkrumah and Charles De Gaulle: Two Nationalists in Historical Contact," undated and, typescript (Box 4)
    (of lecture, "Kwame Nkrumah and Charles De Gaulle: Two Nationalists," presented November 1970)
  - "Language Policy in Uganda After Idi Amin," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Leadership in Africa: Obote of Uganda undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The Legacy of Racial Betrayal: Lessons from Shaka, Shakespeare and Puccini," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - Lemuel Johnson and Rovan Locke, "Cuba's Castro and Africa's Castration: A Case-Study in Micro-Dependency," conference paper, November 1978, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The Liberal Revival in Black Africa," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Libya and Chad: A Betrothal is Announced," WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Libya: A 'Super-Power' in Miniature?" WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Mahatma Gandhi and the Black Man: Domestic and International Aspects," lecture October 1971, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The Making of an African Political Scientist: A Study of Origins," commissioned for International Social Science Journal, 1972-1973, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Marxist Theories, Socialist Policies, and African Realities, pub. in Problems of Communism September-October 1980 (Box 4)
    (with article drafts)
  - "Mau Mau and MPLA: Comparative Self-Reliance in Liberation Movements," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Micro-Dependency: The Cuban Factor in Southern Africa," (Box 4)
  - "Military Rule and Educational Reform," conference paper January 1972, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Military Rule and the Re-Africanization of Africa; Black Soldiers as a Traditionalising Force," conference paper February 1975, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The Military-Agrarian Complex in the Re-Africanization of Africa: Rustic Soldiers as Traditionalizers," conference paper October 1980, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Milton Obote of Uganda: The Man and the Leader in Politics," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Mobility as a World Order Imperative," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Models of World Order: The Next Thirty Years," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The Moral Dilemma of Salman Rushdie's The Satanic Verses," in Proceedings of the Panel on 'Correction of Erroneous Information Published on Islam and Muslims': The Case of The Satanic Verses, undated (Box 4)
  - "The Moral Paradigms of the Superpowers: A Third World Perspective," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The Moving Cultural Frontier of World Order: From Monotheism to North-South Relations," conference paper July 1980, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The Multiple Marginality of the Sudan," conference paper February 1968, typescript (Box 4)
  - "A Muslim's View of Africa and the West," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Nasserism and Religion," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The National Service and Economic Conscription in Uganda and Tanzania," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The National Service as an Initiation Ceremony," lecture March 1970, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Chapter 12: Nation-Building and the Kinship Polity," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Negritude, the Talmudic Tradition and the Intellectual Performance of Blacks and Jews," conference paper March 1976, typescript (Box 4)
  - "New Trends in International Violence: Aerial Terrorism," September 1970, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Nigeria and the United States: The Need for Civility, the Dangers of Intimacy," (Box 4)
    (reprint from Orbis, Winter 1982)
  - "Nigerians Debate Their Global Role," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Niger-Saki: Does Nigeria Have a Nuclear Option?" undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Nkrumah, Obote and Vietnam," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The Novelist as a Mediator Between Art and Social Philosophy, conference paper December 1976, typescript (Box 4)
  - "A Nuclear Cloud by the Star of David?" undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Nuclear Proliferation and the Search for Pax Africana," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Numerical Strength and Nuclear Status in the Politics of the Third World," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Obote of Uganda: The Political Man and the Political Leader," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Obote's Document No. 5: Electoral Polygamy and the Future of Tribal Politics in Uganda," conference paper, August-September 1970, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The Old Makerere and the Legacy of Tom Mboya," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "On Poets and Politicians: Obote's Milton and Nyerere's Shakespeare," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "On Race and Rights: Four Fields of Action," May 1968, typescript (Box 4)
  - "On Revolution and Nakedness," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "On Values," March 1976, typescript (Box 4)
  - "One Man's Nkrumah," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Opposing the Motion," Note from Main Hall Debate 1968, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Partition, Democracy -- And the Assassin," 1968, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The Patriotic Mind and The Literary Imagination in East Africa," conference paper August 1968, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The Persistence of Ethnocracy," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - Mazrui "Phallic Symbols in Politics and War: An African Perspective," (Box 4)
    (in Journal of African Studies," Spring 1974)
  - "Piety and Puritanism Under a Military Theocracy: Uganda Soldiers as Apostolic Successors" (Box 4)
    (undated reprint from Sage Publications, and conference paper, October 1973)
  - "Piety, Politics and Personality," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "A Pilgrimage to Uganda," January-February 1981, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The Poetics of a Transplanted Heart," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Political Culture and Economic Socialisation in East Africa," conference paper January 1968, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Political Culture and National Integration in Uganda," lecture, October 1969, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The Political Environment of the University of East Africa," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The Political Geography of Radical Coups," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Political Nostalgia," Ibadan Journal of Humanistic Studies, October 1981 and, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Political Reform and the Quest for Discipline in East Africa," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Political Revolutionaries and Economic Innovators," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Political Science and Political Futurology: Problems of Prediction undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Political Science and Social Commitment Across Two Republics of Uganda," lecture July 1971, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Political Science and the Decline of African Nationalism," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Political Science at Makerere and Public Affairs in Uganda," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Political Superannuation and the Trans-Class Man," conference paper September 1967, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Political Theory and National Involvement in East Africa," 1968, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Political Thought in Africa: Current Ideological Trends," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Political Trends in Contemporary Africa," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Political Vigilantism and Institutional Void: An Exploratory Essay on Africa Between Nationalism and Nationhood," Mazrui and Victor Olorunsola undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Politics and Drama: Some Areas of Comparison," Mazrui and Molly Mazrui, conference paper December 1970 and "Politics and Drama," undated, typescripts (Box 4)
  - "Population Control and Social Justice," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "The Population Explosion and the Nuclear Mushroom," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Post-Liberation Movements: In Search of Racial, Sexual and Class Utopias," undated, typescript (Box 4)
  - "Post-War Zimbabwe in Search of Peace," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Power and Culture in Africa," outline undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Preliminary Thoughts on Violence," for International Philosophical Conference, Sudan November 1977, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Press in Africa and the United States: Divergent Conceptions of Roles," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Prison Bars of Capitalism and the Barbed Wires of the Nation-State," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Privilege and Protest as Integrative Factors: The Case of Buganda's Status in Uganda," May 1968, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Proceedings in the Tanzanian Parliament," June 1969 (Box 5)
    (handwritten notes)
  - "Programme in Town and Country Planning, Makerere University: Comparative Advantages of Undergraduate and Postgraduate Programmes," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Proposed Task Force on Culture and the World System," project proposal undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Protest," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Public Opinion and the Politics of Family Planning," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - Publications in languages other than English (Box 5)
  - "A Question of Balance," Africa Events April 1987 (Box 5)
  - "Racial Self-Determination," in Macartney, ed. Self-Determination in the Commonwealth, 1988 (Box 5)
  - "Reagan and the Winter of Discontent," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Red Cross and Politics in Africa," paper delivered November 1970, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Reincarnation of the African State," symposium paper undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Religion and Political Culture in Africa," reprint from Journal of the American Academy of Religion, 1985 (Box 5)
  - "Religion and Socialism: The Case of Obote's Uganda," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Residual Anarchy in Uganda," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Re-Tribalization of Politics," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Rhetoric, Oratory and Oral Literature in Africa's Political Experience," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Rise of Nigeria and the Decline of Egypt," WUOM radio broadcast February 18, 1981, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Role of the African University in The Process of Political Development," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Roots -- Does It Mark the End of American Amnesia?" 1976, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Rousseau and Intellectualized Populism in Africa," Mazrui and G.F. Engholm, typescript (Box 5)
    (, reprint from The Review of Politics, January 1968 and conference paper, May 1967)
  - "The Sacred and the Secular in East African Politics" (Box 5)
    (reprint from Cahiers D'Etudes Africaines, 1973)
  - " The Satanic Verses or a Satanic Novel? The Moral Dilemas[sic] of the Rushdie Affair," undated pamphlet, and " The Satanic Verses or a Satanic Novel?" pub. in Africa Events, July 1989 and "Is The Satanic Verses a Satanic Novel? Moral Dilemmas of the Rushdie Affair," pub. in Michigan Quarterly Review, Summer 1989 and "Poetic Hatred: Is The Satanic Verses a Racist Novel?" in West Africa, May 1-7, 1989 (Box 5)
  - "Satyagraha on Safari: A Case Study of Gandhi's Influence in Africa," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Semitic Impact on Black Africa: Arab and Jewish Cultural Influences," (Box 5)
    (reprint from Issue, 1984)
  - "Sexonomy: The Political Economy of Sex and Class," for presentation at African Studies Association October 31, 1979, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Should There Be Anti-Racial Laws in East Africa?" undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Social Conflict and Nation-Building in East Africa," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Social Distance and the Trans-Class Man in Africa," conference paper December 1968, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Social Engineering and Language Policy in East Africa," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Social Policy and Cultural Engineering in East Africa," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Social Policy and the Indian Exodus from East Africa," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Socialism as a Mode of International Protest: The Case of Tanzania," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Soldier, the Socialist and the Soul of Development," conference paper February 1973 (Box 5)
  - "Some Socio-Political Functions of English Literature in Africa," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Southern Africa: Will It Be Kissinger's Next Peace Mission?" written for The Sunday Post, Nairobi, July 14, 1974, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Spotlight on Havana: The Nonaligned Movement Comes to the Americas," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Study of Current History: Political, Psychological and Methodological Problems," conference paper May 1979, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Sub-Imperialism in Africa," WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Swahili and the First World War," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Symbolism of 'Simba': A Study in Imagery," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Tanzania as a Case of Heroic Failure," in The Nigerian Journal of Political Economy, April 1984 (Box 5)
  - 'Technology, International Stratification and the Politics of Growth," conference paper August 1979, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Tensions Between Academic Freedom and Academic Democracy: An African Perspective," conference presentation, January 1972, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Rise of the Lumpen Militariat," part of unidentified mss. undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Thoughts on Protest," May 1968, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Through the Prism of the Humanities: Eurafrican Lessons from Shakespeare, Shaka, Puccini, and Senghor" (Box 5)
    (conference paper, September 1980 typescript and as published in Benson, ed. African Cultural and Intellectual Leaders and the Development of the New African Nations, 1982)
  - 'To 'The Africans' and Back: The Aftermath of a Television Series," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Tom Mboya and Kwame Nkrumah," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - 'Tom Mboya and the Struggle Against Uganda's Isolationism," undated, typescript (Box 5)